James Everett Perdue Papers
State University of New York at Oswego
- Correspondence-Robert Greenleaf, 1977 - 1990 (Box-folder 1-25)
  Incoming and outgoing, handwritten and typed, correspondece between Robert Greenleaf and Dr. Perdue. A note from JEP, "Letters to Robt Greenleaf, author. comments on his ideas + Mss." Additional correspondents include: Hugh G. Lally, Promotion Director, Paulist Press Ralph L. Spencer, Acting Provost, SUNY Oswego Constantine B. Simonides, Coference Convener, Center for Applied Studies, Conference on Undergraduate Leadership Potential, Nashville, Indiana. Rev. Oliver F. Williams, C.S.C., University of Notre Dame. Larry Spears, Executive Director, The Robert K. Greenleaf Center. - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - "Is It More Blessed To Give Than To Receive?" by Robert K. Greenleaf. Excerpt from Friends Journal, Quaker Thought and Life Today. May 1, 1976. photocopy. 2 pp. Commencement talk by Michael Greenleaf [handwritten note - "18 year old grandson"], Solebury School, New Hope, Pa. June 5, 1976. 3 typed pages. "Robert Greenleaf: The gentle taskmaster of servant leaders". 2 pp. Not cited. n.d.
- Correspondence, January, 1977 - March, 1977 (Box-folder 1-26)
  Personal correspondence pertain to Dr. Perdue's move to Albany, New York, from Oswego. Incoming and outgoing correspondence. Handwritten and typed. Correspondents include: Margaret A. Smith, Administrative Assistant to the President, SUNY College @ Old Westbury. Lew O'Donnell, SUNY Oswego David W. Pelland, Menter/Rudin/Trivelpiece Law Offices, Syracuse, New York Mrs. George L. Richardson, Syracuse, New York. Norris W. Goldsmith, Oswego, New York. Joan Van Keuren, Director, Student Financial Aids, SUNY Oswego Father Hall, St. Mary's Church, Oswego, New York Sandy Sternlicht, SUNY Oswego Vernon A. Tryon, SUNY Oswego Dr. Girgis Ghobrial, SUNY Oswego Albert W. Brown, President, SUNY Brockport T. William Hall, Syracuse University Gary T. Durham, Director of Security, SUNY Oswego Jean W. Eddy, SUNY Oswego Kenneth E. Young, President, The Council on Postsecondary Accreditation. John J. Connolly, President, Dutchess Community College, Poughkeepsie, New York. Robert Johns, Robert Johns & Associates, Rapid City, South Dakota. Joseph V. Julian, Syracuse University Robert E. Wehrle, Regional President, Marine Midland Bank, Syracuse, New York. John S. Toll, SUNY Stony Brook Thomas F. Powell, SUNY Oswego John T. Bernhard, President, Western Michigan University Craig Shaw Fehlhaber, Graduate Assistant, Department of Industrial Arts and Technology. George N. Rainsford, President, Kalamazoo College, Kalamazoo, Michigan Geoff Lilndsay, Editor, the Oswegonian Arthur Sabatini, SUNY Oswego Foster Brown, Pompano Beach, Florida Louis T. Benezet, SUNY Stony Brook Judi Brownell, SUNY Cortland Dr. Clark D. Ahlberg, President, Wichita State University, Wichita, Kansas. President Howard J. Burnett, Washington and Jefferson College, Washington, PA President Elmer Jagow, Hiram College, Hiram, Ohio Dr. Carroll V. Galbreath, Assistant Regional Commissioner for Postsecondary Education, Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Dallas, Texas. Mrs. Olla Rickett, Tampa, Florida
- Correspondence, April, 1977 - December, 1977 (Box-folder 1-27)
  Personal correspondence to and from Dr. Perdue pertaining to his move from Oswego to Albany, New York. Incoming and outgoing. Handwritten and typed, including carbon copies. Correspondents include: Bruce Dearing, University Professor of Humanitites in Medicine, SUNY Upstate Medical. Lynn D. Hemink, SUNY Oswego Susan Fratkin, National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges. Henry Angle, Fulton, New York. Dr. James A. Smith, Oswego, New York Grace Maxon, Oswego, New York. Claire M. Merlehan, Oswego, New York Dr. Joseph H. Johnson, Chairman, Presidential Search Committe, National College of Eduction, Wilmette, Illinois. Mrs. Edward Siegel, Roslyn, New York Hilda G. Bohall, Oswego, New York Mr. & Mrs. L.V. Lieb, Oswego, New York Fred Plank, SUNY Oswego William P. McGoldrick, Director, Community Relations + Development, SUNY Oswego Dr. Virginia Radley, Acting President, SUNY Oswego Dr. James Soluri, SUNY Oswego Dr. Jerry Exline, SUNY Oswego Raymond Doersam, SUNY Oswego Layden E. Brown, Chairman, Oswego College Council Dr. Frank Robinson, Vice President for Administrative Affairs, SUNY Oswego Mrs. Roland Clark, Oswego, New York Albert Hoefer, Jr., Ithaca, New York Lester J. Gosier, Bay Shore, New York William H. Green, Oswego County Savings Bank, Oswego, New York. Harold Schwartz, President, JOMAR Plastics, Port Chester, New York Lester J. Gosier, Chairman Science Department, Bay Shore Union Free School District. Dr. James Gemmell, Associate Director, Academic Collective Bargaining Information Service, SUNY, Albany, New York. William J. Purvis, Oswego, New York Hugo Groppi, Director, SUNY Program Abroad, Pisa, Italy. President Donald E. Walker, Southeastern Massachusetts University. Attached is 13-page paper, "New Policies for Changing Institutions". Dr. Ernest L. Boyer, Commissioner of Education, Department of Health, Education + Welfare. Alvin Goldberg, Chairperson, Department of Speech Communication, University of Denver. Dr. Donald R. Mathieu, Dean of Arts and Science, SUNY Oswego W.H. Cowley, Palo Alto, CA. Dr. James F. Kelly Cynthia Parsons, Education Editor, The Christian Science Monitor, Boston, Massachusetts. Harold G. Cassidy, Professor-at-Large, Hanover College, Hanover, Indiana. Asa G. Hilliard, Dean, School of Education, San Francisco State University, San Francisco, CA. Joseph Duffey, Chairman, National Endowment for the Humanities, Washington, D.C.
- "A Response to the 70's" report, March, 1973 (Box-folder 1-28)
  A Response to the 70's. State University College at Oswego's Reply to the 1972 Master Plan of State University of New York. First Draft. March, 1973. James E. Perdue, President. 94 pp. Table of Contents: Introduction I. The Region, The State, and Admissions Regionalism Admissions programs Freshman class profile Transfer students Gifted high school students II. The Academic Programs General studies Energy studies Communications programs Programs of interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary nature "Classical College" Teacher Education Continuing education of teachers Technical studies Career studies Health science Practicum Honors programs International education Graduate programs Interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary programs Lifelong learning III. Faculty and Staff Consultation on programs existing and proposed Equal opportunity employment procedures Excellence in teaching Non-teaching professionals Student affairs Research IV. The Student and Campus Life Time-shortened degrees Deferred admissions and "step-out" programs External degrees Off-campus programs Practicum and internships Intercultural understanding Retirees and senior citizens Student rights Library Campus School Alumni, community and public affairs V. The Seventies
- Publication, n.d. (Box-folder 1-29)
  "Morsels for Meditation, Gleanings Over the Years" by James E. Perdue. 76 pages. A second copy was added. It includes additional pages and expanded sections. The book includes passages / quotes from books and magazines collected over the years by Dr. Perdue. They have been arranged into ten catagories: Administration Deans & Presidents Leadership Learning Liberal Education Morality--Honor--Ethics Power Religion Teaching Communication -- Writing In addition is inserted [not attached to original spiral binding] is "The Career Development Quiz". 6 pp.
- President's Statement, 1969 (Box-folder 1-30)
  1969 two-page statement concerning pilot program. (3 copies)
- Requests for Department Statements, 1965 - 1966 (Box-folder 1-31)
  Correspondence, memorandums and statements concerning a request from Dr. Perdue to department chairs and administrative officers. Dr. Perdue asks that two statements be submitted concerning outstanding characteristics and limitations and a second statement concerning administrative philosophy and role. Included are responses from George F. Lambert, Dean of Men; R. W. Rock; the Dean of Women; the Dean of Students; the Division of Student Personnel. A one-page typed meeting agenda, May 27, 1966 is included.
- Justification, requests, promotions, job vacancies, 1971 (Box-folder 1-32)
  35 typed memorandums and correspondence with attachments that include justification for position reports. Correspondence is between James E. Perdue and State University of New York administration. Correspondents include: Dr. Ernest L. Boyer Dr. James A. Frost Dr. Harold Delaney Thomas J. Peterson Dr. Harold Delaney Harvey Randall
- Speeches-audiotapes, 1959 - 1974 (Box-folder 1-33)
  5 audiotapes contain speeches by Dr. Perdue. Dates range from 1959 to 1974. All audiotapes are TDK Professional Master Series. IECI/TYpe1 Normal Position. Acoustic Master. AM 60 Identifying handwritten labels on each: Pres. Perdue / Freshman Assembly / 9/19/59. Pres. Perdue / Stillwater / July 31, 1961. Pres. Perdue / 9/17/63 / A+S Faculty. Pres. Perdue Inauguration 1966. SUNY Oswego President Perdue. 8/29/74.
- Speeches, 1965 - 1969 (2-1)
  Speeches and related materials were either written or given by James Perdue. The speeches were given between the years 1965 and 1969. Speeches include messages to the faculty, addressing issues and concerns or were given at special events such as commencements, dinners or conferences. The length of the speeches range up to 29 pages. There are several speeches with the notes attached. Five speeches are also available here on audiotape. These range from 1959-1974 and are addressed to faculty, Inauguration speeches or Assembly speeches. The Post-Modern Mind. Commencement Address. University of Denver. June 11, 1965. Graduate Education: Fact or Fiction. Graduate Luncheon. July 28, 1965. 2 copies. A Communicty of Scholars. General Faculty meeting. September 9, 1965. 2 copies. The Analytic and the Synthetic. Inaugural Address of Dr. Perdue. May 14, 1966. President's Convocation for Freshmen. September 11, 1966. 29 pp. 5 1/2" x 8 1/2" typed pp. Summer Session Conference. Miami. November 1967. 8 typed pages with editing notes. Statement for disruptive activities. 1968. 3 carbon copies. Today in the First Day of the Rest of Your Life. For Special Issue of Oswegonian. President's Message. May 28, 1969. 2 typed pages, carbon copy.
- Speeches, 1970 - 1975 (Box-folder 2-2)
  Speeches are arranged chronologically. This folder is a continuation of folder 02-01. Speeches include: Members of the Graduating Class of 1970. 3 typed pages. The College Community. 2 typed pages. August 5, 1970. September 1970. President's message. 2 pp. carbon copy. The Community and the College: A Challenge for the Seventies. Draft. September 1970. Greetings to Class of 1971 from Dr. Perdue. President's Speech. October 6, 1972. 16 typed pages with editing notes. Draft of President's message. 1 typed page. n.d. Handwritten "speech to new students. 1/12/75" Liberal Education: What Is It? Remarks to the Board of Trustees of the State University of New York, February 25, 1975. J.E. Perdue. 25 typed pages. Award of Merit Dinner speech. May 1975. 4 typed pages. 4 handwritten pages. Speech to the Faculty. Dr. James E. Perdue. September 4, 1975. 3 typed pages. 3 copies American Association of State Colleges and Universities Proceedings, 1975. Article by Dr. Perdue on pps. 15-24. "President to Presidents Lecture." Complete 83-page journal. President-to-Presidents Lecture. 15th Annual Meeting of American Association of State Colleges and Universities. November 12, 1975. 11 typed pages. 2 copies.
- Speeches, 1975 - 1976 (Box-folder 2-3)
  Speeches 1975 Speech to the Faculty, 3 pp. 1976 speech, "A Framework for Change", 6 pp. 2 copies Draft of Oswegonian editorial by President Perdue. June 1976 Speech to New Faculty. August 30, 1976. Handwritten speech to General Faculty. September 13, 1976 Small folder of speeches, some edited copies on a variety of subjects. 1976 43-page speech on the nature/function of colleges and universities. No title, date or further citing.
- Photographs, n.d. (Box-folder 2-4)
  Five photographs mounted for a display. Group photograph - Dr. Perdue, center; Virginia L. Radley, right. Unidentified gentleman on the left. Dr. Perdue on a bicycle Dr. Perdue with six individuals [students?] and bicycle. Dr. Perdue with large group of students on campus near Hewitt Union.
- 1970's- Student Unrest, 1964 - 1970 (Box-folder 2-5)
  1970's- Student Unrest Various materials such as newspaper articles, magazine articles and miscellaneous memos, newsletters, position papers and pamphlets that approach the problems of and reasons behind the student unrest are included in box 3. Five reports by The University of Denver including - "The Workshop on Liberal Arts Education" 7 pp, 1964 April 1969 "Discipline Code for the University of Denver" 30 pp April 1969 "Code of Procedures for all Agencies" 11 pp 1969 memorandum from Chancellor Maurice B. Mitchell concerning the attached "Declaration of Student Demands" 14 pp 1969 "Principles of Student Life at the University of Denver". 2 pp June 1969 article from "Higher Education and National Affairs" publication, "Consensus on Handling Campus Disorders Urged by National Commission". 7 pp Congressional Record, 91st Congress, "Congress Looks at the Campus: The Brock Report on Student Unrest". 7 pp "Mid-Elders To The Rescue" by Stan Haring, WE:HE/ME System for human relations founder. 2 pp 20-page publication of the EFL College Newsletter, 1970. "Guidelines on University Organization" published by the Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada. 17 pp "Campus Disorders 'Are You Ready For This?'" by the Association of Physical Plant Administrators, April 1970. 6 pp "Just Law & Civil Order" pamphlet, Christopher News Notes, May 1970. May 1970 letter from Robert F. Goheen, Princeton University, to Princeton Alumni, Parents and Friends. 3 pp "Overcommunication or A Forgotten Right: The Right to Affirm", address by Daniel J. Boorstin, June 7, 1970. 12-page pamphlet University of Buffalo memorandum from Thomas T. Frantz, Secretary pro tem, June 1970. Press release from Harvard University, June 1970 from the office of the Vice Chancellor concerning the election and class schedules. 2 pp. Attached is a 1-page description of Cornell University's Fall Semester Plans. 6-page position paper "in opposition to the 'Princeton Plan' for a political-activity recess in colleges and universities in the Fall of 1970." by Keith Spalding, President, Franklin and Marshall College, June 1970. Two 1970 letters of correspondence between Logan Wilson, President of the American Council on Education and Randolph W. Thrower, Commissioner, Internal Revenue Service. Attached is June, 1970, 4-page "Guidelines on Questions Relating to Tax Exemption and Political Activities Statement of the American Council on Education". Higher Education and National Affairs publication, June, 1970, "ACE Issues Guidelines About College Political Activity. Tax Exemption". 12 pp. 3-page report by the Board of Trustees of the California State Colleges, "Committee on Faculty and Staff Affairs" concerning salary increases July, 1970. University of Denver newsletter excerpt, "Excerpts From a Letter to a Concerned Parent." 1 page. "Students Assess Their Colleges and Universities: Historical Backgrounds" by Donald T. Williams, Jr., University of Washington. 10 pp. with 2 page bibliography.
- Photographs, 1960's - 1970's (Box-folder 2-6)
  Eleven photographs are identified in detail in Photo record 2001.015.0002. a. - x. Also includes: Three photographs used in a display. Individuals identified: The Perdue Family Eleanor Filburn Gus Silveira
- Correspondence - Jossey-Bass Inc., Publishers, 1977 - 1978 (Box-folder 2-7)
  Corresopndence - Josey-Bass Inc., Publishers Correspondents include: JB Hefferlin, Director of Special Projects, Jossey-Bass Inc., Publishers Dr. Lynn D. Hemink, SUNY Oswego Allen Jossey-Bass, President, Jossey-Bass, Inc. Papers: "Development in Young Adulthood: Characteristics and Competencies in Education, Work, and Social Life" Edited by Samuel Messick. 6 pp. "The Art of Administration" by Dr. Perdue. September 6, 1977. 5 pp. 2 copies. Small informational booklets: Guidelines for Jossey-Bass Authors. 8 pp. Guidelines for Edited Collections. 7 pp.
- Correspondence - Jossey-Bass Inc., Publishers, 1979 - 1982 (Box-folder 2-8)
  Correspondence - Jossey-Bass, Inc., Publishers Four paper folders inserted in the folder include: 1979-1981: 1981 1981 + n.d.
- Journal Articles and Reports, 1964 - 1973 (Box-folder 3-1)
  Journal Articles and Reports Articles include" "Education in Utopia" by Bruce Dearing, from "Alumni Review", Lebanon Valley College, 1964. 4 pp. "Education and Research" from Ford Foundation Annual Report, 1968. 1 page. "The University and Student Dissent" by Robert S. Morison, from "Science", March 1969. 1 page 2-page excerpt from U. S. News and World Report, July, 1969, "Needed Immediately: 200 College Presidents". "The Hampton Institute Strike of 1927, A Case Study in Student Protest" by Edward K. Graham, reprint from "The American Scholar" 15 pp. Includes "Postscript: The 1969 Demonstrations" by Margaret Mead. "The New Left and the Old Law" by William A. Stanmeyer, reprinted from the "American Bar Association Journal", April 1969. 5 pp. "Co-Ed Living" by Betty Rollin from "Look" magazine, 1969. 6 pp. "Danger: proceed at the risk of rationality" by Robert J. Schaefer. "Relevance or Revolt" by Edmund W. Gordon. Both from "Perspectives on Education", 1969. 16 pp "Where is all began - Berkeley, 5 Years Later, Is Radicalized, Reaganized, Mesmerized" by A. H. Raskin from The New York Times Magazine, 1970. 18 pp. "Dr. Pitzer Looks at the '70's" from Alumni Almanac, 1970. 1 page. "The Spirit of '70, Six Historians Reflect on What Ails the American Spirit" from Newsweek, July, 1970. 16-page excerpt including the following articles: "The Age of Rubbish" by Richard Hofstadter. "We Will Meet As Enemies" by Andrew Hacker. "A Massive Breakdown" by Eugene D. Genovese. "A Case of Hypochondria" by Daniel J. Boorstin. "Again - Don't Tread on Me" by Staughton Lynd. "The Velocity of History" by Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. Time magazine excerpt, October, 1970 - "Investigation, Kent State: Another View". 1 page. Time magazine, November, 1970 - "Man in the Middle" 1 page. Colorado College magazine excerpt, 1970. 16 pp. Included: "A New Kind of Calendar for a Block Course Plan". "The Colorado College Plan: An Academic Program Changes, But a Commitment Does Not" by Barbara M. Arnest. "'Scientia et Disciplina'': The Motto as Background for the New Course Plan" from a memorandum by Glenn E. Brooks. "To Decide, Introspection, discussion, and lesser decisions, then faculty endorsement of an academic change." "The Student In An Age of Unrest" by N. Edd Miller, President, University of Nevada. 4 page excerpt from "New York State Bar Journal", February, 1971. "The Squaring of America" 4 page interview with Herman Kahn. "The Recovery of Civility, Notes for the Long Trek Back" by Ferdinand Mount. Reprint of July 1973 "Encounter". 8 pp. "New Threats to Academic Freedom" by John H. Bunzel. 4 pp. Higher Education and National Affairs excerpt, Vol. XVIII, No. 24. "Nine Presidents List 'Practical Lessons' Of Campus Disruption". 2 pp.
- Campus Unrest - Newspaper clippings, 1970 - 1974 (Box-folder 3-2)
  Campus Unrest - Newspaper clippings The National Observer, May, 1970, "On Campus: A 'Malaise' or a 'Deterioration in Values'?" Excerpts from speeches by Vice President Spiro Agnew and Kingman Brewster, Jr., Presdient of Yale University. 1 page. The National Observer, May, 1970, "Attacking Crisis Rhetoric, A Minority Report on the Woes of the Cities" by James Meahger. "How to Prevent the Destruction of the University", address by Leland C. Marsh, May 1970. "Much Talk But Little Action on Campus Reform" by Fred M. Hechinger, August 1970, New York Times article. "Blazers and Slacks: New Police Image" by Martin Arnold, New York Times article, August, 1970. 2 pp. New York Times article, 1970, "Brewster Explains Campus Unrest" by Peter Kihss. Palladium TImes article, September, 1972, "Need Some New Values, He Says". Los Angeles Times article by Robert J. Dolan, "Social Struggle in U.S. Pits Middle Class Against Upper Middle Class, Says Author." National Observer article, July, 1973, "Sifting Revolution's Ashes for Salvage" by Fred Hechinger. New York Times, April, 1974, "The Mood on Campus" by Leslie Epstein. "Winds of change hit academic world" by Dr. Benjamin Fine. "Student Trustees a Small Minority" by William K. Stevens. "Heyns is Leaving a Placid Campus" by Wallace Turner. "Combat on the Campus" by Dr. Max Rafferty. "Regents Asked to Keep Angela Davis". "U.C. Prof. Raps Angela Ouster". "Governor Urges Link to Students" by Bill Kovach. New York Times article. "Many Are Schooled, But Few Are Educated" by Russell Kirk. "Youth's Faith.. ." "Hitch Warns U.C. Faculty To Change" by Larry Spears. "Campus Violence Decried by Bundy, Ex-Harvard Dean Assays Future of Universities" by M. A. Farber.
- Student Unrest-newspaper clippings, 1969 - 1970 (3-3)
  Student Unrest-newspaper clippings Newspaper clippings pertaining to student unrest include: "Radicals Cause Concern" reprint from 'The Breeze', Madison College newspaper, 1969. New York Times, June, 1969, "Gardner Decries College Violence". "Evans Lauds Parents at Graduation". 2 pp. "College Students Are Unbelievably Innocent" by John Roche, National Observer, January, 1970. "The Ideal Of the University" by Robert Paul Wolff book review by Peter Brooks. The New York Times Book Review, January 1970. "Student Participation" by Ursula Von Eckardt, January, 1970. "USC Takes Giant Strides Under Topping" by William Trombley. Reprinted from Los Angeles Times, April, 1970. 5 pp. "A Student's Plea: Don't Let Radicals Win by Default" by Steven Kelman, The National Observer, April, 1970. "College Urged to Develop Better Links to Students" by David E. Rosenbaum, April 1970, The New York Times. "On Moderation", Palladium Times, May, 1970. "It's Time To Stop Apologizing To Youth" by Dr. K. Ross Toole, copy of May 1970, St. Louis Globe Democrat article. "Proffesor says adults must grab the reins" by Dr. K. Ross Toole, Post Standard, May, 1970. "U.C. Grads Like New Rites" by Larry Spears, Oakland Tribune, June, 1970. "32 States Fight Campus Unrest", New York Times, June, 1970. "Middle American: The Country's New Hero?" by James Meagher, The National Observer, January, 1970. "Indictment of Universities Examined" by John E. Corbally, Jr. "Universities: For Campus Freedoms", November, 1970. "Defenders of Campus Freedom", November, 1970.
- Student Unrest - Kent State, 1970 (Box-folder 3-4)
  Student Unrest - Kent State Newspaper articles, journal article and Kent State magazine are included. "Kent State Students Protest Grand Jury Charges". "Death on the Campus", The Des Moines Register, May, 1970. "Some Kind of Insanity", Chicago Daily News, May, 1970. "Kent and Its College: The Chasm Widens" by Richard T. Cooper, reprint from the Los Angeles Times, June, 1970. 2 pp. "Kent" magazine. June 1970. 28 pp.
- SUNY Oswego newspaper clippings, 1967 - 1970 (Box-folder 3-5)